Guide to the Joseph Magliacano Papers and Photographs WAG.223
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Joseph Magliacano Papers and Photographs
circa 1913-1997
1923-1997
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Magliacano, Joseph
Maglin, Richard
Joan, Landzberg
WAG.223
2.25 Linear Feet in two records cartons, one manuscript box, and one oversized folder.
Joseph Magliacano (July 11, 1897-September 1997) was a labor activist in New Jersey and New York City. The collection contains correspondence and poetry, and notebooks, speeches and materials related to the United Furniture Workers of America (UFWA); it also includes photographs related to Joseph Magliacano's labor union activities (particularly the UFWA) as well as some personal and family photographs.
Historical/Biographical Note
Joseph Magliacano (July 11, 1897-September 1997) was a labor activist in New Jersey and New York City. He was born in San Mango Piemonte, Italy, a village near Salerno, to a farming family some of whose members also worked in nearby textile factories. He immigrated to the New York City in 1913, where he became a barber. Not long after his arrival in the United States, he joined the labor movement and got involved in leftwing politics. In 1915 he joined a barbers' union, and in 1917 the Socialist Party; in the 1920s and early 1930s he began to work as a union organizer for textile and shoe workers, as well as organizing a relief organization for striking coal miners in Pennsylvania, West Virginia, and Kentucky. He also organized Italian immigrant textile workers in New Jersey and participated with them in the historic Passaic Strike of 1926, and appeared in the semi-fictional, semi-documentary film, The Passaic Textile Strike(1926), as himself.
In 1935 Magliacano was appointed organizer for Local 140 Upholstery International Union (UIU), AFL, and participated in successful drives to organize bedding and springs workers. In December 1937, he was one of the delegates to a conference of breakaway UIU locals that led to the founding of the United Furniture Workers of America (UFWA). In 1939, he was appointed organizer for the Newark, New Jersey-based Local 92 of the UFWA. He then remained with Local 140--serving as an elected officer in various capacities, as well as a business manager--until his retirement in 1968. He also ran for political office on the Communist Party of the United States ticket--in 1933, as a candidate for the New York State Assembly (for Kings County, Brooklyn, 3rd District), in 1936, as a candidate for the United States House of Representatives (for New York City's 13th District), and was active in the Italian American anti-fascist movement.
Related Archival Materials
There is a lengthy oral history interview (tape and transcript) with Joseph Magliacano at the American Labor Museum/Botto House in Haledon, New Jersey, on the subject of the 1926 Passaic textile strike.
The Passaic textile strike [videorecording] / produced by International Workers' Aid. New York, N.Y.: Museum of Modern Art, c[198-?], silent, black and white, 40 minutes running time.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence and poetry, and notebooks, speeches and materials related to the United Furniture Workers of America (UFWA); it also includes photographs related to Joseph Magliacano's labor union activities (particularly the UFWA) as well as some personal and family photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Richard Maglin and Joan Landzberg, children of Joseph Magliacano, in 1998. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1998.010, 1998.011, and NPA.1998.012.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into two series; folders are arranged alphabetically by topic within Series I, and mostly chronologically within Series II.
Series I: Papers, 1923-1997
Series II: Photographs, circa 1913-1989
Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Italian American labor leaders.; Italian American communists.; Magliacano, Joseph; United Furniture Workers of America; Maglin, Richard; Joan, Landzberg
- Papers, 1923-1997
  - Awards, Certificates, 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Material, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Health Care, 1975-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Health Care and Senior Citizens, 1973-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Magliacano, Lillian (Lee), 1957-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Poetry, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Poetry, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Poetry, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Poetry, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Poetry, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Poetry, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Publications: Articles by and about JM, 1956-1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - United Furniture Workers of America, 1991-1992; 1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - United Furniture Workers of America: Journal, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - United Furniture Workers of America: Sticker, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 060)
  - Writings (Notebooks), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Writings (Notebooks), 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Writings (Notebooks), 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Writings (Notebooks), 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Writings, Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writings, Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writings, Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings, Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings, Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1920s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Writings, Speeches, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Photographs, circa 1913-1989
  Scope and Content Note
  112 photographic prints, all are black and white, with the exception of three color prints. Three are also oversized. Folder of materials on testimonial dinner dance held in honor of Joseph Magliacan includes original front cover for album that contained this group of photographs and booklet distributed at the event that contains a photograph, brief biographical sketch and greetings from Magliacano's friends, family, and supporters.
  - 1920s, circa 1920-1929 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1930s, circa 1930-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1940s, 1941-1942, 1944-1945, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1940s, circa 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1950s, circa 1950-1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Testimonial Dinner - Dance in Honor of Joseph Magliacano given by Local 92, United Furniture Workers - AFL-CIO, at Hotel Robert Treat, Newark, New Jersey., March 12, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Local 92 United Furniture Workers First Pensioners Dinner, circa March 21, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Testimonial Dinner and Dance [for Joseph Magliacano's retirement] Held at the Forum Room, Thomm's Restaurant, Newark, New Jersey, April 26, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1960s, circa 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1980s, circa 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Personal/Family Photographs, circa 1913-1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Oversized Photographs, 1939, 1941, 1956, undated (Box Shared Tamiment OS002)